Technical University of British Columbia fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Technical University of British Columbia fonds
1988 - 2002
F-177
Q105635645
11.15 m of textual records and other material
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION Fonds includes 72 photographs, 88 negatives, 4 contact sheets, 14 videocassettes, 3 audio cassettes, 1 compact disc, and 2 artifacts. PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION Physical description: 1 photograph located in F-177-1-12-0-3 Physical description: 28 photographs located in F-177-1-16-0-43 Physical description: 1 photograph located in F-177-1-16-0-80 Physical description: 13 photographs located in F-177-1-16-0-107 Physical description: 1 photograph located in F-177-1-18-0-21 Physical description: 1 photograph located in F-177-1-18-0-25 Physical description: 1 photograph located in F-177-1-18-0-28 Physical description: 1 photograph located in F-177-2-1-0-11 Physical description: 2 photographs located in F-177-2-1-0-12 Physical description: 21 photographs located in F-177-2-1-0-13 Physical description: 2 photographs located in F-177-2-1-0-14
Technical University of British Columbia
The Technical University of British Columbia had its roots in the Fraser Valley University Society, a group of concerned citizens founded in February 1991 to lobby government for the creation of a university in the Fraser Valley. On February 2, 1995, the Society's efforts were rewarded when Premier Mike Harcourt announced that $100 million would be provided for the establishment of a technical university in Cloverdale. According to the "Statement of Government Purpose" that was issued for the university, there was to be an emphasis on access, applied research, innovative programs, and the use of new learning technologies. Partnerships were to be developed with private industry to decrease operating costs, and there would be a unique governance structure.
On May 1st 1995, thirteen people were appointed by the Minister of Skills, Training and Labour to an Interim Planning Council (IPC), which was to provide advice to the government regarding the mandate and characteristics of the "Technical University of British Columbia" (TechBC); the first meeting of the IPC took place on June 10th. The original terms of reference for the University were delivered by the Ministry on May 8th, and on August 10th the original constitution and bylaws were registered, under the name "Technical University Society of British Columbia." The first President of TechBC, Dr. Bernard Sheehan, an original IPC member, was appointed on January 1, 1996. On September 27, 1996 the IPC presented its final report to the Provincial Government, and on October 19th the twenty member Council was replaced by a five member Interim Governing Board.
The establishing legislation for the Technical University of British Columbia, Bill 30, was introduced on June 9, 1997, and the Government announced a $2.8 million operating grant for the University. On July 28th, Bill 30 received its third reading; however, the lack of a union, tenure, and a senate in the proposed governance structure prompted the Canadian Association of University Teachers (CAUT) to protest the bill. When the "Technical University of British Columbia Act" was eventually proclaimed on December 5, 1997, CAUT boycotted the new University. The first meeting of the Board of Governors was one week later, on December 12th. An Academic Planning Board was created in place of a senate and on May 8, 1998, the CAUT boycott was lifted.
During this entire period, the University's location was a source of controversy and dispute. The Cloverdale site was deemed unsuitable and, eventually, on July 20, 1998 it was announced that the University campus would be constructed at Surrey City Centre. On October 14th, TechBC's Education and Information Centre at Surrey Place Mall was officially opened, although some students had been attending classes offered through other universities at that location since September 10th. The first ninety students for TechOne, the required first year program for TechBC students, did not begin classes until the following September, and the official opening ceremony for the University was held at Surrey Place Mall on October 14, 1999. A few weeks earlier, on September 23rd, a second announcement had been made confirming plans to construct a 450,000 square foot campus at Surrey City Centre; the development project, scheduled for completion in 2003, would be a joint venture with ICBC, the City of Surrey, and the Provincial Government. In July 2000, the amount of space allocated to TechBC at Surrey Place Mall was increased to 110,000 square feet.
When it opened, TechBC offered Bachelor of Science and Master of Applied Science degrees in three program areas: Information Technology, Interactive Arts, and Management and Technology. In May 2000 the University received government approval for a PhD. program in Applied Science to begin in February 2001.
TechBC Corporation, a wholly-owned, for revenue subsidiary of TechBC, was created in October 1999 in order to establish partnerships with private industry, conduct applied research, and develop and support new businesses.
In September 2000 Sheehan resigned, and the search for a new President began; Dr. Jean Watters was selected, and he began his term in August 2001. His term, however, would be a short one. In May 2001 a Liberal government had been elected in British Columbia. After months of investigation into the TechBC situation, the Government withdrew its support of the University. On February 7, 2002 it was announced that TechBC would be closed at the end of the academic year, and its students and modified programs transferred to Simon Fraser University, although the Surrey campus would remain in use. Watters' last day as President was March 20, 2002.
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on the name of its creator.
Fonds consists of records relating to the activities of the Office of the President and the Board of Governors. Activities, events and topics documented include the establishment and development of TechBC and its programs; early governance, including the activities of the Interim Planning Council and the Interim Governing Board for TechBC; meetings of the Board of Governors and various other university committees and boards; campus development; budgeting, fundraising, and other financial management activities; human resources management; public relations activities; and external co-operation and liaison activities, including TechBC's relationship with the Provincial Government.
Records include terms of reference, minutes, agendas, and supporting papers; correspondence; reports, papers, proposals, academic plans, and working papers; subject files; audit reports, budgets, grant applications, and financial statements; reference manuals and policy statements; contracts and agreements; personnel files and job descriptions; course outlines, program outlines, and academic calendars; presentations and speeches; booklets, brochures, and promotional material; press releases, newspaper articles, journal articles, and newsletters; photographs; videocassettes; audio cassettes; architectural drawings; and artifacts.
The material was arranged into series according to provenance.
Sheehan, Bernard; Watters, Jean; Technical University Society of British Columbia; Moving images; Artefacts; Photographic materials; Textual records; Education; Science and technology
The records were donated to the Simon Fraser University Archives by the Technical University of British Columbia in 2002.
Additional material has been accessioned but not yet processed (as of October 2004: 9.67 m., 1995-2002). Please consult the archivist for information about using these materials; restrictions may apply. No further accruals are expected.
For other material relating to the Technical University of British Columbia, see the finding aid to the Fraser Valley University Society, F-171.
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as required by law. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
File and item lists are available.
- Office of the President records, 1986 - 2002; F-177-1; 8.65 m of textual records and other material; Dates of creation: Predominant dates of the series are 1995-2002. Physical description: Includes 46 photographs, 3 contact sheets, 14 videocassettes, 3 audio cassettes, 1 compact disk, and 2 artifacts. Physical description: 1 photograph located in F-177-1-12-0-3 Physical description: 28 photographs located in F-177-1-16-0-43 Physical description: 1 photograph located in F-177-1-16-0-80 Physical description: 13 photographs located in F-177-1-16-0-107 Physical description: 1 photograph located in F-177-1-18-0-21 Physical description: 1 photograph located in F-177-1-18-0-25 Physical description: 1 photograph located in F-177-1-18-0-28; Technical University of British Columbia. Office of the President
  The Office of the President reported to the Board of Governors. In August 2000, the Office consisted of the President and Vice-Chancellor; VP Business and Finance, VP Research and External Affairs, and VP Academic; Associate Vice-President; Legal Counsel; Director of Communications and Community Relations; Budget Analyst and Secretary to the Board of Governors; Executive Assistant to the President; and Administrative Assistant to the Associate Vice-President.
  published
  Series consists of records relating to the activities of the President and Office of the President of the Technical University of British Columbia. Activities, events and topics documented include activities of the Interim Planning Council, Interim Governing Board, and university committees and boards; academic issues, including academic and program planning activities, as well as research and external affairs activities; campus and administrative structures development; community relations activities; financial and fundraising activities; human resources, information services, legal affairs, and systems management; as well as external co-operation and liaison activities. Series also includes records relating to TechBC, accumulated by the Office of the President for reference or historical value.
  Records include correspondence; reports, papers, proposals, briefs, business, education and academic plans; terms of reference, minutes, agendas, and supporting papers; presentations and speeches; manuals; course outlines, program outlines, and academic calendars; personnel files, job descriptions, contracts and letters of appointment; financial statements, grant applications, audits, and budgets; agreements; legislation; membership information; booklets, brochures, and promotional material; press releases, newspaper articles, journal articles, newsletters; event notices and invitations; notes; videocassettes, audiocassettes, photographs; architectural drawings; and artifacts.
  The material was arranged into sub- and sub-sub-series according to the original filing system of the creator. Wherever possible, material within sub- and sub-sub-series was arranged according to the original filing system of the creator; in some instances, however, it was necessary for the Archivist to provide the arrangement.
  Sheehan, Bernard; Watters, Jean
  The records were in the continuous custody of the Technical University of British Columbia prior to transfer to the University Archives.
  No further accruals to the series are expected.
  Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as required by law. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
  File and item lists are available.
  - Academic Planning Board records, 1997 - 2001; F-177-1-1; 10 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records relating to the activities of the Academic Planning Board. Records include terms of reference, minutes and supporting papers, and membership lists.
    The arrangement was provided by the archivist. Files are arranged chronologically.
    Technical University of British Columbia. Board of Governors. Academic Planning Board
    A file list is available.
    - Academic Planning Board - general, 1997 - 2000; F-177-1-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 177-1)
      Textual records
      Pending review
    - Academic Planning Board - membership list, 1998 - 1999; F-177-1-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 177-1)
    - Academic Planning Board - terms of reference, 1998; F-177-1-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 177-1)
    - Academic Planning Board meeting, 1999/10/06, F-177-1-1-0-4 (Archival box - standard 177-1)
    - Academic Planning Board agenda, 1999/10/06, vol. 1, F-177-1-1-0-5 (Archival box - standard 177-1)
    - Academic Planning Board agenda, 1999/10/06, vol. 2, F-177-1-1-0-6 (Archival box - standard 177-1)
    - Academic Planning Board meeting, 1999/11/17, F-177-1-1-0-7 (Archival box - standard 177-1)
    - Academic Planning Board meeting, 2000/01/19, F-177-1-1-0-8 (Archival box - standard 177-1)
    - Academic Planning Board meeting, 2001/09/26, vol. 1, F-177-1-1-0-9 (Archival box - standard 177-1)
    - Academic Planning Board meeting, 2001/09/26, vol. 2, F-177-1-1-0-10 (Archival box - standard 177-1)
  - University committee and board records, 1998 - 2001; F-177-1-2; 32 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records relating to meetings of the Board of Governors, and the President's Executive Advisory Committee. Records include minutes and supporting papers, and reference manuals.
    The arrangement was provided by the archivist. Files are arranged first alphabetically according to committee and board, and then chronologically.
    Technical University of British Columbia. Board of Governors; Technical University of British Columbia. President's Executive Advisory Committee
    For other material relating to the President's Executive Advisory Committee (PEAC), see the President's Office Files sub-series, F-177-1-12.
    - Board [of Governors] binder (Deana), 1998 - 2001; F-177-1-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 177-1)
    - Board of Governors reference manual, vol. 1, 2000; F-177-1-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 177-1)
    - Board of Governors reference manual, vol. 2, 2000; F-177-1-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 177-1)
    - Board of Governors meeting, 2001/10/03, vol. 1, F-177-1-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 177-2)
    - Board of Governors meeting, 2001/10/03, vol. 2, F-177-1-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 177-2)
    - PEAC Meetings, April to Sept. 1999, vol. 1, F-177-1-2-0-6 (Archival box - standard 177-2)
    - PEAC Meetings, April to Sept. 1999, vol. 2, F-177-1-2-0-7 (Archival box - standard 177-2)
    - PEAC Meetings, April to Sept. 1999, vol. 3, F-177-1-2-0-8 (Archival box - standard 177-2)
    - PEAC Meetings, April to Sept. 1999, vol. 4, F-177-1-2-0-9 (Archival box - standard 177-2)
    - PEAC Meetings, April to Sept. 1999, vol. 5, F-177-1-2-0-10 (Archival box - standard 177-2)
    - PEAC Meetings, July 1999 to August 2000, vol. 1, 1999 - 2000; F-177-1-2-0-11 (Archival box - standard 177-3)
    - PEAC Meetings, July 1999 to August 2000, vol. 2, 1999 - 2000; F-177-1-2-0-12 (Archival box - standard 177-3)
    - PEAC Meetings, July 1999 to August 2000, vol. 3, 1999 - 2000; F-177-1-2-0-13 (Archival box - standard 177-3)
    - PEAC Meetings, July 1999 to August 2000, vol. 4, 1999 - 2000; F-177-1-2-0-14 (Archival box - standard 177-3)
    - PEAC Meetings, July 1999 to August 2000, vol. 5, 1999 - 2000; F-177-1-2-0-15 (Archival box - standard 177-3)
    - PEAC Meetings, July 1999 to August 2000, vol. 6, 1999 - 2000; F-177-1-2-0-16 (Archival box - standard 177-3)
    - PEAC Meetings, September 2000 to August 2001, vol. 1, 2000 - 2001; F-177-1-2-0-17 (Archival box - standard 177-3)
    - PEAC Meetings, September 2000 to August 2001, vol. 2, 2000 - 2001; F-177-1-2-0-18 (Archival box - standard 177-3)
    - PEAC Meetings, September 2000 to August 2001, vol. 3, 2000 - 2001; F-177-1-2-0-19 (Archival box - standard 177-4)
    - PEAC Meetings, September 2000 to August 2001, vol. 4, 2000 - 2001; F-177-1-2-0-20 (Archival box - standard 177-4)
    - PEAC Meetings, September 2000 to August 2001, vol. 5, 2000 - 2001; F-177-1-2-0-21 (Archival box - standard 177-4)
    - PEAC Meetings, September 2000 to August 2001, vol. 6, 2000 - 2001; F-177-1-2-0-22 (Archival box - standard 177-4)
  - Academic issues records, 1995 - 2002; F-177-1-3; 97 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records relating to TechBC's establishment and development of academic and research programs; policies and procedures; and collaboration with external research, science and technology based organizations. Records include reports, proposals and business plans; correspondence; minutes, agendas, and supporting papers; agreements; applications and requests for proposals; program outlines; terms of reference; presentations; booklets, brochures, and promotional material; annual reports; notes; and press releases.
    - Academic issues - general records, 1996 - 2002; F-177-1-3-1; 41 cm of textual records
      Sub-sub-series consists of records relating to the establishment and development of academic programs, policies, and procedures for TechBC. Activities and topics documented include faculty and staff policy and procedures; academic planning; student admissions, scholarships, and tuition; course and program development; activities of the Degree Program Review Committee; development of an Education Management System; faculty meetings; activities of the Program Advisory Committees for the Information Technology, Interactive Arts, Management and Technology, and Multimedia Studies programs; student council development; and activities of the University Review Committee, Faculty Promotions Committee, and TechBC Award Committee. Records include reports and proposals; minutes, agendas and supporting papers; correspondence; program outlines; terms of reference; requests for proposals; and notes.
      The material was arranged according to the original filing system of the creator. Files are arranged alphabetically.
      Technical University of British Columbia. Board of Governors. University Review Committee; Technical University of British Columbia. Degree Program Review Committee; Technical University of British Columbia. Information Technology Program Advisory Committee; Technical University of British Columbia. Management and Technology Program Advisory Committee; Technical University of British Columbia. Multimedia Program Advisory Committee; Technical University of British Columbia. Faculty Promotions Committee; Technical University of British Columbia. TechBC Award Committee; Technical University of British Columbia. Interactive Arts Program Advisory Committee
      - Academic faculty/contract staff, 1998; F-177-1-3-1-1 (Archival box - standard 177-4)
      - Academic plan, 1998; F-177-1-3-1-2 (Archival box - standard 177-4)
      - Academic program planning, 2000; F-177-1-3-1-3 (Archival box - standard 177-4)
      - Admissions, 2001; F-177-1-3-1-4 (Archival box - standard 177-4)
      - BC Student Assistance Program (BCSAP), 1998; F-177-1-3-1-5 (Archival box - standard 177-4)
      - Co-op education, 1998 - 2000; F-177-1-3-1-6 (Archival box - standard 177-4)
      - Course calendar 1999/2000, 1998 - 1999; F-177-1-3-1-7 (Archival box - standard 177-4)
      - Degree Program Review Committee (DPRC), vol. 1, 1996 - 2002; F-177-1-3-1-8 (Archival box - standard 177-4)
      - Degree Program Review Committee (DPRC), vol. 2, 1996 - 2002; F-177-1-3-1-9 (Archival box - standard 177-5)
      - Degree Program Review Committee (DPRC), vol. 3, 1996 - 2002; F-177-1-3-1-10 (Archival box - standard 177-5)
      - Degree Program Review Committee (DPRC), vol. 4, 1996 - 2002; F-177-1-3-1-11 (Archival box - standard 177-5)
      - Degree Program Review Committee (DPRC), vol. 5, 1996 - 2002; F-177-1-3-1-12 (Archival box - standard 177-5)
      - Degree Program Review Committee (DPRC), vol. 6, 1996 - 2002; F-177-1-3-1-13 (Archival box - standard 177-5)
      - Degree Program Review Committee (DPRC), vol. 7, 1996 - 2002; F-177-1-3-1-14 (Archival box - standard 177-5)
      - Degree Program Review Committee (DPRC), vol. 8, 1996 - 2002; F-177-1-3-1-15 (Archival box - standard 177-5)
      - Degree Program Review Committee (DPRC), vol. 9, 1996 - 2002; F-177-1-3-1-16 (Archival box - standard 177-5)
      - Education Management System (EMS), vol. 1, 2001; F-177-1-3-1-17 (Archival box - standard 177-5)
      - Education Management System (EMS), vol. 2, 2001; F-177-1-3-1-18 (Archival box - standard 177-5)
      - Education Management System (EMS), vol. 3, 2001; F-177-1-3-1-19 (Archival box - standard 177-6)
      - Educational Technology and Learning (ET and L), 1999; F-177-1-3-1-20 (Archival box - standard 177-6)
        Open
      - Executive MBA program (TechBC), 2001; F-177-1-3-1-21 (Archival box - standard 177-6)
      - Faculty advance, June 21-22, 2000, F-177-1-3-1-22 (Archival box - standard 177-6)
      - Faculty meetings, 1999; F-177-1-3-1-23 (Archival box - standard 177-6)
      - Faculty Promotions Committee, 2001; F-177-1-3-1-24 (Archival box - standard 177-6)
      - Information technology, 1998; F-177-1-3-1-25 (Archival box - standard 177-6)
      - Interactive arts, 1998 - 2000; F-177-1-3-1-26 (Archival box - standard 177-6)
      - Management and technology, 1998; F-177-1-3-1-27 (Archival box - standard 177-6)
      - Orientation week, 1999; F-177-1-3-1-28 (Archival box - standard 177-6)
      - PhD programs at TechBC, 2000; F-177-1-3-1-29 (Archival box - standard 177-6)
      - Program Advisory Committees - general, 1999 - 2001; F-177-1-3-1-30 (Archival box - standard 177-6)
      - Program Advisory Committee - information technology, 1998; F-177-1-3-1-31 (Archival box - standard 177-6)
      - Information Technology Program Advisory Committee meeting, November 9, 1998, F-177-1-3-1-32 (Archival box - standard 177-6)
      - Program Advisory Committee - interactive arts, 1998; F-177-1-3-1-33 (Archival box - standard 177-6)
      - Program Advisory Committee - management and technology, 1998; F-177-1-3-1-34 (Archival box - standard 177-6)
      - Management and Technology Program Advisory Committee meeting, November 16, 1998, F-177-1-3-1-35 (Archival box - standard 177-6)
      - Multimedia Studies Program Advisory Committee meeting, November 12, 1998, F-177-1-3-1-36 (Archival box - standard 177-6)
      - Program planning - general, 1998 - 1999; F-177-1-3-1-37 (Archival box - standard 177-7)
      - Program proposals, vol. 1, 1999; F-177-1-3-1-38 (Archival box - standard 177-7)
      - Program proposals, vol. 2, 1999; F-177-1-3-1-39 (Archival box - standard 177-7)
      - Scholarships, 1999 - 2001; F-177-1-3-1-40 (Archival box - standard 177-7)
      - Student council, 2001; F-177-1-3-1-40.1 (Archival box - standard 177-7)
      - TechBC Awards Committee, 2000; F-177-1-3-1-41 (Archival box - standard 177-7)
      - TechOne, [ca 1998]; F-177-1-3-1-42 (Archival box - standard 177-7)
      - Tuition fees, 1999 - 2000; F-177-1-3-1-43 (Archival box - standard 177-7)
      - University Review Committee, 2000 - 2001; F-177-1-3-1-44 (Archival box - standard 177-7)
    - Research and external affairs records, 1995 - 2002; F-177-1-3-2; 56 cm of textual records